[Music]
- Eric thank you for making the time
where we're going to talk about a couple
of quality articles that have come out
quite recently and talking about the IDW
and the first one was talking about
whether the IDW is intellectually
diverse and then a follow-up article as
well we're going to talk about some of
the criticisms of the article but I'd
like to starts I know that you're a fan
of this tactic by Steele Manning that
particular arguments if you were to
restate the argument in a in a in a way
that you think is more accurate than was
made how would you do that well I think
it's a great question David I think that
part of the problem is that there are a
lot of different skeins running through
this discussion it's hard to pull them
apart one of which is that some people
within the IDW are fans of term
classical liberalism and I'm not
necessarily for it or against it it's
just not a term that I tend to apply to
myself and I don't think that sufficient
care has been taken to say that some
members of the group or movement or
what-have-you
use that label while others do not and
so there's a bit of a pressure at the
moment to say well you guys all call
yourself classical liberals and I just
don't think that that's the case so that
would be the the first sort of steel
Manning is is that I would want the
critique to be more careful about saying
that it's limited to those who identify
as classical liberals and then the
author has every right to try to make
the case that the classical liberal
position is in fact a version turbit ISM
but I certainly don't think of myself as
a classical liberal first and foremost I
think of myself somebody who has
progressive conservative and libertarian
feelings on a variety of different
issues I think that's why all of these
positions continue to be explored with
none no particular political viewpoint
ever becoming dominant because if we're
if we're really truly honest with
ourselves when we say we're conservative
or liberal or or progressive or
what-have-you we're usually talking
about kind of the leading note or tone
that we are expressing and I think that
you know when people are in cautious and
they say well I am a staunch libertarian
or I am a committed conservative then
what they're doing is that they're
exchanging sort of a degree of
resolution for a four degree degree of
clarity and a lot of people appreciate
that clarity on the front end I pay a
fairly heavy price by saying I'm not a
free speech absolutist I'm very much
associated with free speech but there
are a lot ways in which I can't stomach
certain kinds of free speech outcomes
for example child pornography is not
something that I would stand behind
under free speech or from it you know
many of us pay a hefty price for
appearing to purists to be mealy-mouthed
if you will when I said I'm not
necessarily anti tribal I'm not
necessarily you know anti progressive or
Pro progressive or anything like that so
I suppose what I'm thinking is that
there's a critique made of wing if you
will of the IDW as if it was the
totality of the IDW and that wing is
being faulted in the minds of the
authors and others for an insufficient
layer of a level of resolution and I
think that those of us who paid a hefty
price for saying well I'm I can't be
tied to an absolutist position on any of
this stuff really it so because we want
to keep a very high level of resolution
and so I think that there's a series of
trade-offs there's no way of pleasing
everybody I think when it what the
article was trying to do and trying to
say there's there's a further refinement
and that has to do with the fact that if
you brick progressivism or the left or
whatever you want to call it into the
traditional liberal core of the left and
then you augment that with a fairly
recent extremely aggressive upgrade
which appears willing to attack reason
civility as agents of oppression you
know our tools of oppression I think
that the upgrade really what is it at
issue in a question what is it what is
being questioned and if you believe that
upgrade that extremely postmodern
adjustment to classically progressive
positions if you think that is now the
new dominant left and it's not going
away you probably take a fairly
dismissive attitude towards the entire
left-of-center Canon of thought and I
would say that there are members of the
of the IDW who believe that this current
aggressive strain has displaced
classically liberal or classically
progressive positions which will never
return and that we now need to deal with
the fact that that upgrade is permanent
and those people have probably decided
that they are going to abandon any hope
in a left-of-center position well I held
that position that that upgrade if you
will that marginal difference in a level
of aggression and willingness to attack
reason and data and evidence and itself
in favor of tying people in knots
logically and epistemologically I
thought that was permanent I would
understand quickly why do people who are
completely abandoning any kind of
resolution view of the left now it
happens that I understand why they're
saying that but I disagree I believe
that many people are fairly moderate and
liberal in their views and are going
through a period akin to the McCarthy
era which I've called left car theism in
which it's very dangerous to simply say
the obvious which is when you're
attacking reason or one of two genders
or concepts as abstract as patriarchy or
anything like that you've probably made
a fairly significant wrong turn
somewhere in your thinking and while it
might be difficult too dangerous for
most people to explore their own
relatively moderate left-of-center
positions I don't think that'd be
reasonable left or the analytic left or
the traditional apps have gone away I
just think that it's been terrorized
into a sort of hibernating state and I
think that's a that's a major difference
between the sort of right leaning
portion of the idea with you and the
more left-leaning portion of the
activity and I think you know that I may
disagree with the people who are than
the more right leading portion but
that's what makes that's what makes it
interesting certainly why I'm listening
to them and saying who you really think
this is permanent you think this is
never going back now with what's very
new if I understand it correctly is that
Claire is suggesting that we are
caricature the left
he's Claire layman the co-editor correct
that Claire and her author Yuri who
she's publishing for making them hear
frequently that the new upgrade to the
sort of left orthodoxy it's not that
it's new in terms of nobody's ever heard
it before but it's never been as
dominant to my way of thinking as it is
now that that upgrade probably has more
to it than we we would imagine and I
think we're very interested to hear why
Claire believes that we definitely
believe that people are discount
taking too much of what is going on on
the left left a tremendous number of
huge successes with gay marriage
cannabis legalization and you know
greater awareness let's say of gender
fluidity issues I think that these are
all things that you know we're long and
coming and in our super report and I
think that there are sort of
representing the the best qualities of
the left the question of whether the new
highly aggressive strain has something
new to say that's really that's
fascinating I I was kind of unaware that
Claire believed that so if the idea is
that viewing everything through a racial
lens and you know disputing whether or
not lived experience Trump's any kind of
objective of experience if that is in
fact some sort of an innovation I'm
pretty aware of it and I've heard this a
lot I've heard that these ideas are now
carrying the day on the left side of the
aisle because they represent some
understanding about the limits of
rationality and that's one hell of a
meeting I seem to have missed and just
to sort of also steal manner a little
bit from from my side it talks about
that the dividing line now and I think
there's there's some truth in this at
the could it came from an original tweet
that seemed to show that the most of the
members of the IDW were liberal on most
issues and he or he said that it feels
wrong and his his idea was that the
dividing line now I think this is
certainly true online and probably
started with with gamergate and has kind
of developed through then is that the
dividing line now is whether you are pro
or anti what you might call social
justice
activism is kind of characterized as
social justice warrior thinking that
that is now become a big dividing line
hasn't it well I mean I think this is
this is very mysterious I think a lot of
us have traditionally had a very
positive view of social justice it's the
warrior part this kind of vigilantism
that we're having none of I mean I think
all of us are having them and the you
know that just sort of the sort of Glee
with which people are talking about
cancelling human beings and ruining
lives and really excited about the idea
that no platform will be given to or
relatively moderate positions as if
garden-variety Country Club Republicans
or even real Democrats are one step away
from Joseph Goebbels I mean that's the
that's the really weird stuff that I
don't think anybody has any patience
with at all because it's not part of
adulthood because some people would say
that that is is a caricature and most
people on the Left don't believe those
those things there are far more
reasonable people to have conversations
with the won't that wouldn't kind of
degenerate into reason is a tool of the
capsules patriarchy law that that's a
caricature is a very small part of the
left
well then here's the question why is it
that this moderate reasonable EFT
doesn't tell these shrill voices to shut
up
terrify the children our Wilding right
the adults cowering behind their front
doors because nobody wants to be doxed
nobody wants to find that they're
unemployable nobody wants to be shamed
nobody wants to be canceled
nobody wants to be called out
I mean look this is an interesting point
it has to do that that what is now
fueling journalism is outrage and
there's nothing more outrageous than
publishing a story like he had be
friends with white people anymore or I
divorced my husband because he was white
or do men deserve to be government at
all or some you know if you publish
something like that you get a lot of
clicks because it's it's bananas
it's just we're going through a business
model shift and the baby boomers are in
decline their narratives don't work
we've got serious economic problems
we're trying to roll up our sleeves and
come to common purpose we've spent way
too much time denigrating anything that
smacks of patriotism as if all
patriotism was jingoism we're deranged
as the developed world has become
deranged the idea that are supposed
elites who are anything but believe me
I've met them can't figure out why
brexit past they can't figure out why
Hillary Clinton lost really you can't
figure out why if you've caught every
single person who's a restriction ascend
fo which they absolutely aren't most
people who are restriction mister zina
philic it's just based on epithet fear
her shame this portrayal and it's
endless boring and Yuri said in his
article that the big dividing line was
on the attitude to structural oppression
and for example do you you you
identifies on the Left do you do you
believe in structural oppression do I
believe that Robert Moses configured New
York as a planner in order to you know
keep certain parts of the city from
having falling land values or to keep
the races separate but
believe that structural oppression
exists that any smart person does I
don't even understand
well that was URIs point in his article
work that the major dividing line at the
moment is whether you believe or take
into account structural oppression no no
you're confused URIs out of his depth in
my opinion structural oppression exists
everybody knows that it exists I don't
think anybody is seriously disputing
whether structural oppression exists
we're debating what the degree of
structural oppression is so you know as
I've frequently pointed out you have I
think of the top hundred chess players
ninety nine of them are male one of them
is female do you believe that 100% of
that imbalance based on shares of the
population versus shares of the top
hundred chess players is all structural
oppression in a game that doesn't seem
to know which gender is playing God I'm
open to the idea that there's some
structural oppression sure but do I
think that it's 99 to one like you know
it is his chest the most bigoted the
most ferociously backward game in the
universe which is systematically
destroying the lives of female hopeful
chess players I don't even know what
cath way I could imagine that that was
taking place so I think what we're
debating is people who are gleefully
claiming that all imbalances our
structural question if they do not favor
particular groups and he referred to an
S recline article in the first piece
where as reclined talked about the
reactionary right online and it's a it's
an interesting thing to put apart
because in some ways and as you've said
that the IDW is in reaction to certain
things which we can argue about whether
it should be in reaction to or not but
how does it avoid becoming a purely
reactionary
movement and not saying okay there are
certain ideas we need to resist but
there's also a place on the other side
of this where we can resolve some of
these divisions look this is just a very
stark cultural difference do you believe
that the claims of structural oppression
have skyrocketed in fact because
oppression never been lower than it is
currently and people who need a high
level of oppression in order to continue
to claim special privileges are amping
up their claims that the only reason
that imbalance continue to exist could
be strong personal oppression if that's
your perspective and I think we've seen
this with the Southern Poverty Law
Center that group that many of us have
very positive memories of you know
they've got a brick-and-mortar presence
they've got a large endowment and there
are very few Klansmen to hunt so it's
probably a matter of political economy
that you would expect that they would be
looking for enough structural oppression
to justify their ongoing commitments and
operation now that's one perspective
another perspective is gosh we got rid
of all of the ostensibly causes of
oppression and look at how imbalance
things continue to be ergo it must be
cryptic structural oppression and we
have to you know triple our efforts to
hunt it out wherever it is I think that
would be closer to the experience of
those who disagree with the idea and I
think that that's a debate that I would
be interested in having with people on
the other side who subscribe to the same
rules of debate I do I think one of the
places where this has got an entirely
bizarre is that many of us are
encountering the claim reason itself and
civility itself our tools of oppression
and then as soon as we make the
observation that we've encountered such
claims some
says oh come on nobody really believes
that I I cannot figure out what is going
on in the extreme left in terms of faith
argumentation it's almost like a giant
prank that never ends in both of the
obstacles that seems to be quite a focus
on Dave Rubin in particular why do you
think that is and what do you make of it
that's a good question I mean I think
we've all tried to figure out why we're
going through this very bizarre time I
think Davis view of how he is balancing
his portfolio is that he is accepting a
lot of very conservative gigs for
example with turning-point USA or Prager
you or going on Fox and then feeling is
that he's balancing it by saying hey do
you realize you guys just invited a gay
man who smokes weed into your group and
kudos to that for being tolerant so from
his perspective yeah he's doing a lot of
work with conservatives but he's
constantly reminding them that they are
changing and that they are becoming more
tolerant if you walk if you like his
view I think is is that he is making the
the right more liberal now from a
different perspective and in this is
held by many people he is choosing
repeatedly to punch tip left and to
accept right-wing speaking engagements
no right-of-center speaking engage and
so from that perspective well then he's
just really much more on the right and I
think that he's agreed that he's moved
right I don't think that's a question
but I think it has to do with whether or
not you view his balancing of this which
is you know it's quite open about
talking about being pro-choice at a
conservative event and that is a way in
which he is actually taking the left to
the right as he fights the part of the
left that he thinks
is uh has taken the left down and you
know I don't think he makes any bones
about it he doesn't think the left is
ever coming back I think he thinks the
Democratic Party is finished so you know
that's a debate that he and I have I
don't think the Democratic Party is
finished I think that we have to fight
for its soul right now and so that's
what what I think is sort of dividing
people as is the Dave's rhetoric and
Dave strategy is different than my
strategy so you know do I like Dave
strategy better than my strategy now you
know I think he's doing something where
he's you know going on more conservative
programs and I would feel comfortable
with I'm one of the issues that I see a
lot of the criticisms of the left and
I'm thinking particularly of Dave Rubin
and Jordan Peterson possibly because
they're repeated so often they seem to
be quite low resolution and do you agree
and do you think we need higher
resolution critiques of the left I I
think I'm going to be making higher
resolution critiques of the left because
I haven't given up on the left
if I weren't where they are where they
think this is just gone
you know metastatic and there's no
saving it I think it's understandable
why they would move to a lower
resolution picture I think that the the
real fear I have is is much more on the
right that we had the right down to a
couple of zealots with tiki torches and
now the far left is going to antagonize
ordinary human beings to moving farther
and farther right to it to escape an
attack on a reason and civility
themselves so I think that this
stylistic difference it's a difference
in findings of fact I think that I am
I'm much more optimistic this will
bounce back and that we're in a period
of madness and that the madness can't
continue forever but if I thought the
madness we're going to continue forever
sure I might I might just dismiss the
whole thing and I guess by
higher-resolution critiques what I'm
also thinking about is as far as I
understand people only generally change
their minds or even people only
generally listen to you when you
validate experience in terms of
is that for example on the left your
concern about unfairness is a valiant is
a valid concern but I'm concerned I'm
also worried about how that can turn
into an ideology that then doesn't admit
it becomes very simplistic whatever I
mean that's that's what I would consider
a more nuanced perspective what would
you say is the girl that needs to be
made look I've been trying to make this
with URI to very little avail he wants
to say there's more to the position of
the left then we are giving it credit
for my point is I I've always built that
right the standard liberal left has a
lot going for it and that the
progressive left because the traditional
progressive left has had a lot to learn
for the new upgrade to my mind is where
the problems begin and end is what I'm
really interested in is beef be hyper
specific what is it about the Glee with
which we are canceling people we are
terrifying people we are coming after
livelihood we are trying to humiliate
shame and ambiguous people so that they
are terrified to speak out relatively
garden-variety truths and then when they
express fear we say oh come on nobody
believes those really radical things
maybe it's a few college kids with green
hair somewhere in the northwest but and
are you reacting I think this is what's
coming across as gas lately
meaning if
when you say open borders do you mean
open borders if you don't mean put
orders don't say open borders if you
mean open borders let's play through the
consequences of what you're talking
about
you know if you really believe that
every deviation from the percentage in a
population
and are you really bothered by wage gaps
is that really what's bothering you
because I can tell you that in high
fashion modeling I think it favors women
by like ten to one's a men are getting
paid ten cents on the dollar I don't
think anybody seriously cares about that
except as an oddity I don't think
anybody's mystified as to why it's
happened the key problem is is that
we've adopted these very strange speech
patterns like hashtag kill all men what
do you mean by hashtag kill all men oh I
just mean it would be nice if a--world
were a little better for women father I
don't know it system some pattern of
English usage that you know I think I
think the appeal of it and the fun of it
is to get grandpa to scratch his heads
and say wow kids today and there is also
the point being made the IDW needs to
broaden beyond where it currently is and
to move to have more conversations with
people what reasonable leftists or
people outside the kind of auntie left
left-wing bubble you think that that's
true you think those kind of
conversations need to happen
I'm just mystified by this I mean if
you've got Weinstein in your group he
seems to me to be pretty far to the left
I don't think been Pierrot is afraid of
having a conversation with Brett
Weinstein I think that's not what the
issue is the issue is do you want to
have a pseudo conversation with somebody
whose major point is to target like why
would a boxer want to get into a ring
with a gang member
carrying a switchblade hey I don't get
it it's not about boxing it's just about
violating the rules and thinking that
that's clever and cute so you know to
the extent that somebody wants to agree
on the rules they're probably not going
to be representing the social justice
war perspective I mean I don't want to
use the use as an epithet if the
person's point
you is I want to use something other
than reason and civility with which to
talk to you because those are the tools
of oppression we don't even know what
conversation means I mean David I just
think you have to appreciate this is a
giant waste of time
it's a pathetic squandering of political
opportunity to do good forth for the
very people work we're talking about
whether that's trans people poor people
people of color traditionally
marginalized groups you know what we're
talking about is trying to antagonize
the far-right in it do four years of
Donald Trump or something far more
extreme that's how it looked me the only
reason I'm finding this interesting is
that I don't think it's interesting to
torch the entire developed world on
utopian social engineering experiments
run by out of control the azov
psychotics is it's just not a fitting
end to the incredible experiment it is
Western civilization which has finally
come to terms with all of its problems
and all of its benefits you know whether
that's you know the advent of
antibiotics or slavery or Jim Crow or
nitrogen-fixing
I mean there's just some problem with
stupid being in charge this David this
is gone on way too long and it's too
weird it's too creepy and it has to do
with the political economy of the baby
boomer Davos whatever you want to call
it bubble collapsing and pretending that
this is actually some sort of a a an
interesting intellectual left-wing
movement with important points with
people who can um who can make those
points in an intelligent fashion without
name-calling I haven't seen it most of
the things that people are saying that
are reasonable were part of the left
before the current increase in
vigilantes and he
there's a part of this you know all of
this identitarian stuff the
intersectionality intersectionality was
much more interesting when it was
Crenshaw where was at UCLA log back in
like the nineteen eight month you know
baby may be unpacking knapsack and in
the examination of unearned privilege
coming out of Wellesley was initially
interesting but it's it's metastasized
into some kind of a cult-like thing and
nobody it's not cults aren't interesting
because you're just dying to understand
them they're interesting because they've
got your children and your future
hostage right and you just want you want
your family back and you want to start
working on real issues when have
problems you don't want to be afraid to
simply observe what you see with your
own eyes and ears and report on it and
be told you know the your the love child
of Adolf Hitler Benito Mussolini and Pol
Pot Asst
[Music]
you